Guide to the Early Fondren Library manuscripts collection, ca. 1700-1948 MS 018
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Early Fondren Library manuscripts collection
ca. 1700-1948
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888
MS 018
0.5 Linear Feet
This collection consists of an assortment of letters and papers acquired over a period of time and kept together. The collection consists of folders containing correspondence to and from historical / literary figures (Thomas Carlyle, Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz, Jose de San Martin, George Bernard Shaw, Henry David Thoreau, William Wordsworth, and others). The largest part of the collection is correspondence of nineteenth century literary figures.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of an assortment of letters and papers acquired over a period of time and kept together. The collection consists of folders containing correspondence to and from historicaland literary figures (Thomas Carlyle, Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz, Jose de San Martin, George Bernard Shaw, Henry David Thoreau, William Wordsworth, and others). The largest part of the collection is correspondence of nineteenth century literary figures.
Correspondents include St. John Arthur Adcock, Carl Ahrendt, Matthew Arnold, Pierre Augustine Beaumarchais, Robert Williams Buchanan, Anne Isabella Byron, William Samuel Cardell, Thomas Carlyle, Robert William Chapman, Christopher Pearse Cranch, Chauncey Mitchell Depew, Sir Edward Dering, Douglas Southall Freeman, John Galt, Sir John Hart, S.C. Kiang, William H. Lambert, Gottfried Wilhelm Liebniz, Henry Mackenzie, George Moore, Sir John Moore, John Rickards Mozley, Munster-Ledenburg, Thomas Murray, Sir Joseph Noel Paton, Joseph Pennell, John Pintard, Pierre Piquery, Jose de San Martin, James Sayers, George Bernard Shaw, Charles Henry Smith, Robert Southey, A.W. Standing, William Alfred Tattersall, Henry David Thoreau, John R. Vancourt, Henry Van Dyke, Agnes Wakefield, George Parker Winship, Humbert Wolfe, William Wordsworth, Charlotte Mary Younge and others.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This collection is composed of both gifts and purchases made over many years prior to 1960.
Index Terms
Subjects
Authors; Literature
Document Types
letters (correspondence)
Subjects (Persons)
Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950; San Martín, José de, 1778-1850; Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1646-1716; Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850; Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1862
- Series I: Correspondence, ca. 1700-1948, 253357
  - E. Nesbit Bland to Arthur Adcock, March 22, 1910, 253469 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John Oxenham to Arthur Adcock, January 14, 1918, 253468 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John Oxenham to Arthur Adcock, November 13, 1918, 253467 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - W.R. Inge to Arthur Adcock, August 13, 1920, 253466 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - H.M. Steadman(?) to Arthur Adcock, October 20, 1921, 253465 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - W. Pett Ridge to Arthur Adcock, October 7, 1926, 253464 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - W. Pett Ridge to Arthur Adcock, September 8, ?, 253463 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - W.R. Inge to Arthur Adcock, no date, 253462 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Margaret Verdie? to Arthur Adcock, no date, 253461 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carl Ahrendt to Herr Japhet, February 24, 1887, 253460 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of letter from Carl Ahrendt to Herr Japhet, February 24, 1887, 253459 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Matthew Arnold to Bishop of Manchester, August 10, 1875, 253458 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of letter from Matthew Arnold to Bishop of Manchester, August 10, 1875, 253457 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Matthew Arnold to A.H. Dooley, January 31, 1877 (with envelope), 253456 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of letter from Matthew Arnold to A.H. Dooley, January 31, 1887, 253455 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photograph of Matthew Arnold, no date, 253454 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Edward White Benson to R.L. Ottley, September 30, 1890, 253453 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pierre de Beaumarchais to General von Steuben, October 19, 1785, 253452 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert Buchanan to Henry Edwards, April 21, 1884, 253451 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to Fred Dolman, October 23, 1890, 253450 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to F. Stanley, August 3, 1894, 253449 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to Mrs. Evans Bell, March 20, ?, 253448 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to Newcastle Chronicle, July 15, ?, 253447 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to J.G. Wilson, August 18, ?, 253446 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to J.G. Wilson, "Notes in Paris," August 18, ?, 253445 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Buchanan to Serge Redway, November 14, ?, 253444 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lady Byron to Miss Mackenzie, September 5, 1817, 253443 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lady Byron to Mr. George, January 9, 1843, 253442 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Picture of Lady Byron, no date, 253441 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - William Samuel Cardell to General H.A.S. Dearborn, December 8, 1821, 253440 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - W.S. Cardell to Gen. H.A.S. Dearborn, December 17, 1821, 253439 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - W.S. Cardell to unknown, February 22, 1822, 253438 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - W.S. Cardell to Gen. H.A.S. Dearborn, March 8, 1824, 253437 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - W.S. Cardell to Gen. H.A.S. Dearborn, May 24, 1824, 253436 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Thomas Carlyle to J.W. Parker, November 15, 1847, 253435 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Typescript of letter from Thomas Carlyle to J.W. Parker, November 15, 1847, 253434 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - T.J. Wise to Robert W. Chapman, April 1, 1927, 253433 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thomas Chatto to Robert W. Chapman, April 25, 1927, 253432 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - T.J. Wise to Robert W. Chapman, April 28, 1927, 253431 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - unknown (possibly Lawrence Fitzroy Powell) to unknown, no date, 253430 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Richard Cobdon to unknown ("Walmsley"), August 29, 1856, 253429 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Christopher P. Cranch to Mssrs. Welch, Bigelow and Co., February 29, 1872, 253428 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Christopher P. Cranch to unknown, September 18, 1872, 253427 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - George Croly to Dr. Maginn, April 17, 1824 (letter incomplete), 253426 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - George Croly to Mrs. Hemans, May 4, ?, 253425 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Typescript copy of Speech delivered by Chauncey M. Depew to Union League of New York, January 20, 1915, 253424 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sir Edward Dering, document concerning ordinance, 1630, 253423 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Douglas Freeman to Howard Swiggett, October 18, 1948, 253422 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - John Galt, Introduction to "The Proselyte," no date, 253421 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Galt, Typescript of Introduction to "The Proselyte," no date, 253420 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Galt, "The Misanthrope," no date, 253419 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Galt, "The Field of Battle," no date, 253418 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Galt, "The Crusade (fragment)," no date, 253417 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Galt, "The Crusaders March (fragment)," no date, 253416 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - John Galt, "Hymn (to the Sun?)," no date, 253415 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sir John Hart to Lord Grenville, November 4, 1792, 253414 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Typescript of letter from Sir John Hart to Lord Grenville, November 4, 1792, 253413 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lord Grenville to Sir John Hart, December 17, 1792, 253412 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Typescript of letter from Lord Grenville to Sir John Hart, December 1792, 253411 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - W.C. Hazlitt to John Shelley, February 20, 1868, 253410 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - S.C. Kiang to O.A. Morgner, October 5, 1918, 253409 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - S.C. Kiang to O.A. Morgner, October 21, 1918, 253408 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - S.C. Kiang to O.A. Morgner, December 7, 1918, 253407 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - S.C. Kiang to O.A. Morgner, February 1, 1919, 253406 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter of Introduction from S.C. Kiang to Chinese Ambassador in Washington, no date, 253405 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - W.H. Lambert to Brig. Gen. D. Ramsey, July 13, 1864, 253404 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper clipping Re: Speech by W.H. Lambert, no date, 253403 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - G.G. Leibniz to unknown, September 17, 1715, 253402 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Henry Mackenzie to Miss Tyler (?), March 20, 1820, 253401 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - George Moore to Eleanor Ramos, April 5, 1928, 253400 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - George Moore to Eleanor Ramos, April 21, 1928, 253399 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - George Moore to Eleanor Ramos, 1928, 253398 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bond signed by Sir John Moore, May 7, 1690, 253397 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Poem written by Edward N. Mozley (son of J.R. Mozley), January 8, 1917, 253396 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - John R. Mozley to Sir Clifford, May 19, 1917, 253395 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Georg Hubert Munster-Ledenburg to Lady Ailesbury, February 15, 1977 (with envelope), 253394 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Thomas Murrary to Judge Buchanan acknowledging donation, March 29, 1861, 253393 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sir J. Noel Paton to Mrs. Molesworth, January 1, 1885, 253392 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Sidney J. Parsons to Joseph Pennell, May 27, 1925, 253391 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Elizabeth R. Pennell to Sidney J. Parsons, July 5, 1925 (with envelope), 253390 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - John Pintard, Letter to Members of the city and county of New York in Assembly, March 10, 1906, 253389 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pierre Piquery, Bill of Sale in Natchitoches, Louisiana, February 2, 1747, 253388 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Samuel Rogers to Katherine Sharpe (?), 1833 ?, 253387 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Samuel Rogers to unknown (my dear friend), January 5, 1848, 253386 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Jose de San Martin to Dr. William Miller, October 16, 1821, 253385 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - James Sayers, Poem entitled "Mundungus," ca. 1780, 253384 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - George Bernard Shaw to Miss Katherine Pole, October 6, 1908, 253383 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - George Bernard Shaw to Grant Richards, June 23, 1927, 253382 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - George Bernard Shaw to Miss Penrose Fitzgerald, August 10, 1927, 253381 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Charles Henry Smith to Smith family, "My Heartless Home, near Fairfax," October 13, 1861, 253380 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Robert Southey to Richard Sharp, January 20, 1814, 253379 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Robert Southey to unknown, Spring, 1817(?), 253378 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - A.W. Standing, Typewritten synopsis of the Career of Colonel John Laurens of South Carolina, 1932, 253377 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - unknown ("Derby") to William Tattersall, September 12, 1882, 253376 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - unknown ("Argyll") to William Tattersall, September 19, 1882, 253375 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - unknown to unknown, November 5, 1885 (?), 253374 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Henry David Thoreau, Journal entry from "Autumnal Tints," ca. 1859, 253373 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - John R. Vancourt to unknown ("Dear Colonel"), December 8, 1862, 253372 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Lucy L. Cable to Henry van Dyke, July 17, 1907, 253371 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Henry van Dyke to Hardin Craig, no date, 253370 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Typewritten copy of Poem entitled "The Blessed Damozel," no date, 253369 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Agnes Wakefield, Diary entitled "A Visit to Schwabach," May-June 1883, 253368 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sheet of handwritten notes headed "Daniel Press, 1903-1906," March 20, 1911, 253367 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - F.J. Hall to George P. Winship, November 17, 1921, 253366 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Receipt from Oxford University Press to George P. Winship, February 1, 1922, 253365 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - F. Madan to George P. Winship, February 19, 1922, 253364 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - F. Madan to George P. Winship, February 22, 1922, 253363 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Picture of Admiral Blake, no date, 253362 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Humbert Wolfe to Grand Uden, September 1, 1932, 253361 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - William Wordsworth to Frederick Reynolds, ca. 1828, 253360 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Typescript of letter from William Wordsworth to Frederick Reynolds, no date, 253359 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Charlotte Yonge to unknown ("Dear Sir"), March 24, 1900, 253358 (Box 1, Folder 48)